Guide to the Silas B. Dutcher family papers 1977.282
Brooklyn Historical Society
Silas B. Dutcher family papers
circa 1820-1930
Brooklyn Historical Society
Dutcher, Silas Belden
Dutcher family
Dutcher, Edith
Dutcher, Rebecca J. (Rebecca Jacobs)
1977.282
6.34 Linear Feet in seven full manuscript boxes, one half manuscript box, one flat box and one oversize folder.
The Silas B. Dutcher family papers are composed primarily of Dutcher's business and political correspondence during the period 1861 to 1908. Dutcher occupied various political appointments in New York City and Brooklyn during this period, including Supervisor of Internal Revenue, Pension Agent, Appraiser of the Port of New York, and New York Supervisor of Public Works. Additional items in the collection include family correspondence, newspaper clippings, ephemera, family and political scrapbooks, and various certificates awarded to Dutcher.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Lawrence Doggett and the estate of Mr. Meenahan, 1963.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into five series:
Business and political papers, 1861-1908
Family papers, 1889, 1909
Clippings and ephemera, 1858-1913
Scrapbooks, circa 1820-1930
Awards and certificates, 1864-1909
Biographical note
Silas Belden Dutcher (1829-1909) was born in Springfield, N.Y., as the second child of Parcefor and Johannah Low Frink Dutcher. In his early years, Dutcher worked on the family farm and taught school. In 1855, Dutcher moved to New York City and began his mercantile career. He continued to work in trade until 1868, when he was compelled to focus exclusively on his rising political career.
Dutcher's political career had begun in 1856, when he joined the newly-formed Republican Party. He served his first position in public office as Supervisor of the City of New York from 1860 to 1861. In 1868, Dutcher became Supervisor of the Internal Revenue, a position in which he served for four years before being appointed U.S. Pension Agent for the Eastern District of New York by President Ulysses S. Grant. In 1877, Grant appointed Dutcher to the position of Appraiser of the Port of New York, and after serving in this position for three years, Dutcher was made State Supervisor of Public Works by New York Governor Alonzo B. Cornell.
Dutcher also participated on various political committees. He was chairman of the Kings County Republican Committee for four years, a member of the State Republican Committee, and chairman of the Executive Committee in 1876. In 1896, New York Governor Levi P. Morton appointed him to the commission to frame the charter for Greater New York. Dutcher was also a frequent delegate to Republican state and national conventions.
Beyond his political activities, Dutcher maintained his business ties throughout most of his life. From 1877 on, he was the director of Metropolitan Life Insurance. He was a charter trustee of Union Dime between 1859 and 1902, and president of the company from 1885 to 1902. In 1891, he became president of the Hamilton Trust Company.
Beside his active political and business careers, Dutcher was also deeply involved in his family and religious lives. In 1859, he married Rebecca Jacobs Alwaise. Together they lived in Brooklyn and had 8 children over the next 20 years: Dewit Parcefor, Edith, Malcolm, Elsie, Myra, Jessie, and twins Eva and Edna. Dutcher was an involved member of the Dutch Reformed Church, teaching Sunday school and serving as super of the Twelfth Street Reformed Church in Brooklyn for 10 years. He was also a member of the Masonic Fraternity.
Sources:
Bogard, Milo T. Silas Belden Dutcher: Prominent in Politics for Half a Century - His Splendid Record in Important Offices - Successful Also as a Financier - Descending from a Long Line of Sterling Americans. New York: New York Newspaper Men, 1901.
Griffin, Walter Kenneth. The Dutcher Family. New York: New York Geneological and Biographical Record, 1910.
Howard, Henry W.B., ed. The Eagle and Brooklyn: The Record of the Progress of the Brooklyn Daily Eagle ... Together with the History of the City of Brooklyn from Its Settlement to the Present Time. Brooklyn, N.Y.: The Daily Eagle, 1893.
Stiles, Henry R. The Civil, Political, Professional and Ecclesiastical History and Commercial and Industrial Record of the County of Kings and the City of Brooklyn, New York from 1683 to 1884. New York: W.W. Munsell and Company, 1884.
Syrett, Harold Coffin. Studies in History, Economics and Public Law: The City of Brooklyn, 1865-1898. New York: Columbia University Press, 1968.
Whittemore, Henry, comp. Our Colonial Ancestors and Their Descendants. Historical, Genealogical, Biographical. Watertown, N.Y.: Hungerford-Holbrook Company, 1902.
Related Materials
Photographs of Silas B. Dutcher in the portraits collection at CBH (Othmer library, north reference desk).
Dutcher, Silas B., Ramapo Water Company reply to The Controller of the City of New York, 1899. ARC.314, Box: 2, Folder: 51.
Bogard, Milo T., ed. Silas Belden Dutcher: prominent in politics for half a century -- his splendid record in important offices -- successful also as a financier -- descending from a long line of sterling Americans. New York, NY: New York Newspaper Men, 1901. CS71.D88 1901
Scope and Contents
The majority of the collection is comprised of correspondence dating from 1861 to 1908 and relating to Dutcher's long career in business and politics, though there are also several items relating to the Dutcher family and the general social, political, and cultural backgrounds of the New York City area, New York State, and the United States.
Series 1: Business papers contains correspondence comprised of loose letters, letter books, and letter copy books, and involving Dutcher in his numerous official political and business capacities. Series 2: Family papers contains a small amount of correspondence relating to Rebecca and Edith Dutcher, as well as materials relating to Silas Dutcher's death in 1909. The loose clippings and ephemera series relates to a wide range of political and social issues, as well as Dutcher's work as Supervisor of Public Works and his involvement in various political and civic organizations. Series 4: Scrapbooks contains news clippings and ephemera compiled by Rebecca and Jessie Dutcher and relating to general political and business issues, Silas Dutcher's political and business careers, religion, arts, and culture. The items in Series 5: Awards and certificates are primarily made out to Silas Dutcher and are from several organizations and institutions in which Dutcher served in varying capacities.
Separated Materials
One photograph and an album of postcards were removed to the image collection and designated as V1997.025. These items cannot currently be located.
New York (State) -- Officials and employees; United States -- Officials and employees; Businessmen -- New York (State) -- New York; Businessmen -- New York (State) -- Kings County; United States -- Politics and government; Financial records; New York (State) -- Commerce; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs; New York (State) -- Politics and government; New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government; Business; New York (N.Y.) -- Commerce; Programs (documents); Public administration -- New York (State); Public administration -- United States; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs; Public officers; Certificates; Obituaries; Genealogy; Business records; Speeches; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Commerce; Political parties -- United States; Printed ephemera; Political participation -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Scrapbooks; Correspondence; Clippings (information artifacts); United States. Pension Bureau; New York (State). Superintendent of Public Works; Metropolitan Life Insurance Company; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); United States. Office of Internal Revenue; Dutcher, Malcolm; Dutcher, Edith; Union Dime Savings Bank; Dutcher, Silas Belden; Hamilton Trust Company; Dutcher, Rebecca J. (Rebecca Jacobs); Dutcher family
- Series 1: Business and political papers, 1861-1908; 1.67 Linear Feet in four manuscript boxes.
  Scope and Contents
  This series chiefly contains correspondence comprised of loose letters, letter books, and letter copy books. The correspondence spans the entire period covered by the series, and involves Dutcher in his numerous political and business capacities, including Supervisor of the Internal Revenue, Pension Agent for the Eastern District of New York, Appraiser of the Port of New York, New York State Supervisor of Public Works, Director of Metropolitan Life Insurance, President of Union Dime, and President of the Hamilton Trust Company. Additional letters illuminate Dutcher's active role in the Republican Party and his involvement in numerous state and local professional, political, and civic member organizations. The series also includes documents and reports related to certain issues overseen by Dutcher as Supervisor of Public Works, including a legal dispute between the West Shore & Buffalo Railroad Company and the Oxford Copper and Sulphur Company, in which Dutcher was arbitrator, and an application from the West Shore & Buffalo Railroad Company to construct its road over canal lands in Montgomery County. Additional items include financial records, and handwritten and typed transcripts of speeches delivered or received by Dutcher at various events hosted by professional, political, and civic organizations.
  - Letters - contents of letter copy books I-III, 1868-1879 (Box 1, Folder Series 1, 1-9)
  - Loose letters, 1861-1880 (Box 2, Folder Series 1, 10)
  - Business correspondence, 1881-1908 (Box 2, Folder Series 1, 11)
  - Letter copy book IV, 1868-1874 (Box 2, Folder Series 1, 12)
  - Letter copy books, 1875-1884 (Box 2, Box 3)
    Box 2 contains two copy books dated 1875-1879 and 1879-1880. Box 3 contains 4 copy books dated 1880 (indexed), 1880-1882 (indexed), 1882-1884, and 1883-1884.
  - Letter book, NY Customs House, 1878 (Box 4)
  - Political and financial papers (Box 4, Folder Series 1, 13)
  - Arbitration, 1885 (Box 4, Folder Series 1, 14)
    Between W. Shore and Buffalo Railroad Company and Reynolds Dock, Constables Hook, NJ, by Dutcher.
  - Canal lands construction (Box 4, Folder Series 1, 15)
    Reports to Supervisor of Public Works to allow Buffalo RR to construct a road over Canal Lands.
  - Campaign speech texts (manuscript and typed), 1884 (Box 4, Folder Series 1, 16)
  - Various speech texts and notes (Box 4, Folder Series 1, 17)
  - Printed speech texts (Box 4, Folder Series 1, 18)
- Series 2: Family papers, 1889, 1909; 0.1 Linear Feet in four folders.
  This series contains a small amount of correspondence relating to certain members of the Dutcher family, and materials relating to Silas B. Dutcher's death in 1909. The correspondence mostly concerns Dutcher's daughter, Edith, and the prospect of her taking a clerical position in the United States Pension Office, an arrangement made possible by her father. Edith ultimately rejects the offer, owing to family committments at home, but recommends a cousin for the position. The remainder of the correspondence is between Dutcher's widow, Rebecca, and the National Memorial, in which the Memorial requests to receive a photograph of the recently-deceased Dutcher. Additional items relating to Dutcher's death include condolences sent to the Dutcher family from the State of New York, the Hamilton Trust Company, and other organizations and personal friends; and photocopies of obituaries of Dutcher clipped from various newspapers. Finally, the series also includes a typed biography and genealogy of Dutcher, the author of which is unknown.
  - Family correspondence (Box 5, Folder Series 2, 1)
  - Condolences (Box 5, Folder Series 2, 2)
    Sent to family after SBD's death.
  - Obituaries (news clippings) (Box 5, Folder Series 2, 3)
  - Family history (typed copies) (Box 5, Folder Series 2, 4)
- Series 3: Clippings and ephemera, 1858-1913; 0.63 Linear Feet in one manuscript box and three folders.
  This series contains loose newspaper clippings compiled by Silas B. Dutcher and his family throughout the period 1853 to 1909 and relating to a wide range of political and social issues. Certain clippings have been filed together according to their predominant subject matter. These clippings cover such topics as Dutcher's work as Supervisor of Public Works, particularly in regard to the management of New York's canals; Dutcher's private and family lives; trade laws; the New York Customs House; the death of New York Tribune editor Horace Greeley; and the financial scandal involving Tammany Hall's William "Boss" Tweed, among others. All remaining clippings have been grouped together as either miscellaneous or general political clippings. There is also one page clipped from an 1862 French-language newspaper, the contents of which seem to relate to certain events of the American Civil War.
  The series also contains several pieces of ephemera relating to Dutcher's involvement in the Republican Party and various other political and civic organizations, including the Brooklyn Masonic Veterans, the Grand Army of the Republic U.S. Grant Post No. 327, and the Department of Parks of the Boroughs of Brooklyn and Queens. These items include announcements for and invitations to banquets and dinners; progams for commemorative ceremonies; circulars relating to Republican candidates in various elections; and the honorary ribbon worn by Dutcher as a Kings County Delegate to the 1904 New York State Republican Convention. Other items seem to relate to Dutcher's personal interest in American history, such as images of Abraham Lincoln and Alexander Hamilton, and handwritten copies of correspondence between Ulysses S. Grant and Robert E. Lee regarding the surrender at Appomattox Court House that ended the Civil War. Additional ephemeral items relate to the Dutcher family and include Sunday school cards and awards for Edith and Malcolm Dutcher; a children's coloring book; and a program for an opera at the Century Opera House.
  - Loose clippings (Box 5, Folder Series 3, 1)
  - Political clippings (Box 5, Folder Series 3, 2)
  - Customs house and trade laws clippings (Box 5, Folder Series 3, 3)
  - Tweed scandal clippings (Box 5, Folder Series 3, 4)
  - Family life clippings (Box 5, Folder Series 3, 5)
  - Sentinelle de Thibodaux clipping (Box 5, Folder Series 3, 6)
  - Political ephemera (Box 6, Folder Series 3, 7)
  - Family ephemera (Box 6, Folder Series 3, 8)
  - Lee-Grant facsimile correspondence (Box 6, Folder Series 3, 9)
- Series 4: Scrapbooks, circa 1820-1930; 2.17 Linear Feet in two full manuscript boxes, one half manuscript box, and one oversize box.
  This series consists of five large scrapbooks containing news clippings and ephemera compiled by Dutcher's wife, Rebecca, and his daughter, Jessie. Two of the scrapbooks contain articles clipped from various New York newspapers and relating to Dutcher's political and business careers, as well as several broad political and business issues. Together, these two scrapbooks offer an exhaustive account of the general political and business climates of the New York City area, New York State, and, to a lesser extent, the United States, from the mid-19th to the early 20th centuries. The remaining three scrapbooks also include articles on Dutcher's careers, but mainly focus on the personal interests of Rebecca and Jessie. These scrapbooks contain clippings of articles on theater, fine arts, literature, fashion, culinary arts, religion, Brooklyn history, and general social and cultural news. Clippings containing obituaries of personal friends, prominent New York citizens, and national celebrities are also included. While the clippings mainly relate to the New York City area, they also contain information on national and international events and issues. A variety of ephemera is also included in these three scrapbooks, including programs for theatrical productions, recitals, and lectures; commencement and excercise programs from various Brooklyn schools, including Girls' High School and Pratt Institute; programs for various community events; marriage invitations and announcements; advertisements; and images of performers and celebrities. One of these latter scrapbooks is housed separately from the rest of the collection in an oversize box.
  - Playbills (kept by Jessie Dutcher), 1906-1924 (Box 6)
  - Clippings, 1873-1894 (Box 7)
  - Clippings, 1875-1877 (Box 7)
  - Clippings, 1895-1906 (Box 8)
  - Mrs. Dutcher, 1853-1900 (Box 9)
    Contains newsclippings, playbills, and other miscellany.
- Series 5: Awards and certificates, 1864-1909; 1.77 Linear Feet in 2 folders and one oversize box.
  This series contains honorary certificates and certificates of appointment from several organizations and governmental bodies in which Silas B. Dutcher served in varying capacities. Represented institutions include the Twelfth Street Reformed Church, the Long Island Historical Society (now the Brooklyn Historical Society), the Brooklyn and Long Island Sanitary Fair, the Holland Society of New York, the Brooklyn Masonic Veterans, the American Academy of Political and Social Science, the Kings Park State Hospital, the Society of Old Brooklynites, the Grand Army of the Republic U.S. Grant Post No. 327, the Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York, the Department of Internal Revenue, the Sunday School of Memorial Presbyterian Church, the Mechanics' Savings Bank of Brooklyn, and the Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences. Some of the certificates are housed separately from the rest of the collection in an oversize box. The series also includes one certificate awarded to Edith Dutcher by the City of Brooklyn Department of Public Instruction.
  - Awards to Jessie Dutcher (Box 8, Folder Series 5, 1)
  - Awards and certificates to Silas B. Dutcher (Box 8, Folder Series 5, 2, Box OS-6)